Guide to the Ezra Cornell Papers, 1746-1888
Cornell, Ezra Papers, 1746-1888
- Series I. Correspondence 1746-1878
  - Correspondence :: Ezra Cornell Correspondence
    - Correspondence :: Ezra Cornell Correspondence :: 1865-1866
      - February 15, 1866 - February 26, 1866 (Box 27, Folder 11)
        Cornell, John H.; Cornell, E.B.; Finch, F.M.; Esty, William W.; Cornell, D.B.; Selkreg, J.H.; Rooker, Thomas N.
      - February 27, 1866 - March 12, 1866 (Box 27, Folder 12)
        Western Union Telegraph Company; Ezra Cornell portrait; Wisconsin lands; prospectus for Illinois College; New York State canals; New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents and others.
        Chester, E.W.; Wright, George B.; Millard, Ira; Chace, Elijah C.; Turner, J.B.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Wood, O.S.
      - March 13, 1866 - March 14, 1866 (Box 27, Folder 13)
        Cornell University: buildings; Ithaca and Towanda Rail Road Company; Cornell Public Library.
        March 14, 1866. Draft report of the Committee on Buildings.
      - March 15, 1866 - March 29, 1866 (Box 27, Folder 14)
        Ithaca and Towanda Rail Road Company; New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents and others; phrenology; Phrenological Journal; telegraph industry; Wisconsin lands; agriculture; Cornell University: founding, establishment of Library; Western Union Telegraph Company; Telegraph Association.
        March 17, 1866. John Stanton Gould to Ezra Cornell:
        "When I learn whether your views correspond with mine in relation to the religious teaching at the University, I will write to you my ideas with regard to a few other fundamental matters connected with the plan of the University."
        May 25, 1866. Draft of a letter by Ezra Cornell:
        "I expect thus to appropriate the balance of my life, and the labors which I have selected, the building up of a first class University, will afford an abundant field. If, however the loyal men of the State should aquiesce in the partiality of my neighbors, and call upon me to discharge the delicate and responsible duties of Governor, I may feel bound to yield to their wishes, and should do my best to discharge the duties honestly and conscienciously."
        Bavaria.
        Rooker, Thomas N.; Gould, John Stanton; Curtiss, George; Dix, Dorothea L.; Whitlock, William; Chace, Albert H.
      - March 30, 1866 - April 11, 1866 (Box 27, Folder 15)
        New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents and others; telegraph industry; Land Grant Act; tax exemptions; Wisconsin lands; animal cruelty; agriculture; Western Union Telegraph Company; Ithaca and Towanda Rail Road Company; Ezra Cornell portrait; Cornell University: buildings, plan; Cascadilla Place.
        Cornell, D.B.; Cornell, W.J.; Nivison, S.S.; Pinkham, F.W.
      - April 13, 1866 - May 6, 1866 (Box 27, Folder 16)
        Cornell University: buildings, plan, founding; Wells College; Wisconsin lands; Jewett's Paleontological Cabinet; Western Union Telegraph Company.
        April 13, 1866. Ezra Cornell to Henry Wells:
        "Your grounds at Aurora also afford a beautiful and healthy location for such an institution. ?I shall venture a suggestion. It is this, that instead of building a Female Seminary at Aurora, which would be but one of an hundred like institutions scatered over our state, and which though it flourished while you lived, and it was fostered by your care and judgment, might soon dwindle and droop when your fostering hand was withdrawn by death, built at Ithaca, "The Wells female department of the Cornell University" and thus aid us to engraft female education in America."
        Also iterates the financial arrangements pertaining to the founding of Cornell University.
        Wells, Henry; Jewett, E.; White, Andrew Dickson; Horner, John; Wood, M.B.; Kelly, William.
      - May 7, 1866 - May 20, 1866 (Box 28, Folder 1)
        Land scrip; Wisconsin lands; Cornell University: location, buildings; collections offered for sale; DeRuyter Institute.
        May 15, 1866. Andrew Dickson White to Ezra Cornell discussing building plans.
        Bell, J.E.; Wright, G.B.; White, Andrew Dickson; Chace, E.C.
      - May 21, 1866 - May 31, 1866 (Box 28, Folder 2)
        Offer of natural history collection; Wells College; telegraph business correspondence: stock; Land Grant Act; Cornell University: buildings.
        May 21, 1866. Geo. Geddes to Ezra Cornell:
        "I have received a letter from Mr. Selkreg informing me that the men of Tompkins Co. will present your name to the Union Convention this fall for the office of Governor?"
        May 22, 1866. Henry Wells to Ezra Cornell:
        "?I was still under the necessity of differing with you in your opinions regarding the connection of a female department to your University; in a few words I will say that the object of this institution is to make one of higher standard than those refered to in your letter & prepare young ladies to be wives & mothers to educate the rising generation who are to take our places & influence & direct the destinies of a great nation, feeling and appreciating a mothers influence attending through a whole life, has induced me to begin an institution to promote a higher standard to moral & intilectual culture than has yet been attained by the ordinary village & town institutions to which you allude, this has been a dream of my life?. I will then have an institution that will educate American girls to fulfil the duties & take the possition that a kind Providence has assigned to the better half of our race in this broad land & woman then can fulfill her mission without going to the polls or entering the areana of politicks."
        May 25, 1866. Thomas Hillhouse, New York State Comptroller, to Ezra Cornell:
        "?I am hopeful that as you have a greater interest in the formation of a permanent and ample endowment for the Institution than any other individual, we may agree on some plan under which you can become the purchaser of the scrip held by the State, with such provision as to the disposal of the proceeds as will conform with what I conceive to be the requirements of law."
        Geddes, George; Wells, Henry; Chace, Miller; Hillhouse, Thomas; Homer, J.; Bell, J.A.; Chace, Theophilus; Brown, Amos.
      - June 1, 1866 - June 13, 1866 (Box 28, Folder 3)
        American Express Company; Cornell University: buildings; American Institute; phonography.
        June 9, 1866. Ezra Cornell to Thomas Hillhouse, State of New York Comptroller detailing Ezra Cornell's proposed use of the land scrip.
        Sampson, W.S.; Cornell, D.B.; Greeley, Horace; Brown, Amos; Graham, Andrew J.
      - June 14, 1866 - July 2, 1866 (Box 28, Folder 4)
        Western Union Telegraph Company; telegraph business correspondence: stock; Cornell University: buildings, natural history collections; Land Grant Act.
        Cornell, Mary E.; Chace, Elijah C.
      - July 3, 1866 - July 23, 1866 (Box 28, Folder 5)
        Photo-lithography business; Cornell University: buildings; telegraph business correspondence: stocks; Minnesota lands; Wells College.
        July 4, 1866. Andrew Dickson White to Ezra Cornell:
        "I have heard of a new candidate for the Presidency of the University -- a Massachusetts judge of high standing. I confess that I would prefer some such man to a clergyman."
        Page, John R.; White, Andrew Dickson; Kelly, William; Greene, J.N.; Rooker, Thomas N.; Miller, Stephen; Wells, Henry; Chester, E.W.; Bell, J.E.; Read, J.M., Jr.; Gould, Sara E.
      - July 24, 1866 - August 4, 1866 (Box 28, Folder 6)
        Western Union Telegraph Company; land scrip; Michigan lands; telegraph business correspondence: stocks; cattle.
        August 4, 1866. Thomas Hillhouse to Ezra Cornell, receipt for bonds for the purchase of land scrip owned by the State.
        August 4, 1866. from Albany:
        "The struggle is over at last and I have just mailed 200 pieces of land scrip to Mr. Woodward and have written him that we will start for the west by Tuesday the 14th?
        "I will however say that at last I have got it to suit me, [and] fully controll all the land scrip for four years whither I take and locate the whole or not. Cook or the Peoples College, and other colleges are powerless to trick or trouble it. I now feel for the first time that the destiny of the Cornell University was fixed, and that its ultimate endowment would be ample for the vast field of labor it embraces, and if properly organized for the developement of truth, industry and frugality it will become a power in the land which will controll and mold the future of this great state, and carry it onward and upward in its industrial developement, and support of civil and religious liberty, and its guarenty of equal rights and equal laws to all men."
        Cornell, Alonzo B.; Wood, O.S.; Curtiss, George; Hillhouse, Thomas; Cornell, Mary Ann.
      - August 6, 1866 - August 29, 1866 (Box 28, Folder 7)
        Steam agricultural machinery; Western Union Telegraph Company; sheep; Cornell University; Kansas lands; telegraph business correspondence; Wisconsin lands.
        August 24, 1866. Ezra Cornell to T.G. Alvord from Eau Claire, Wis.:
        "I have just returned from a trip of three days in the pineries of the Chippawa sleeping two nights in such rude camp as we could construct of pine bows by the application of half an hours labor. Yesterday morning we were aroused from our slumber by the howling of a pack of wolves of a dozen or more counting by the noise and varying voices. They remained with us an hour and then mooved slowly on untill their howl was lost in the distance.
        "?I have not time to write to Senator White. Please show this to him, and say that this land operation is going to be a success. It requires skill, hard work and capital, but all those it shall have, and the present and future youth of our State shall enjoy the blessings that shall flow from a richly endowed Institution of learning."
        Horner, J.; Palmer, O.H.; Cornell, D.B.; Chace, E.C.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Chace, Theophilus; Putnam, H.C.
      - August 30, 1866 - October 5, 1866 (Box 28, Folder 8)
        Cattle; land scrip; Cornell University: students, natural history collections; telegraph business correspondence: stocks; Cascadilla Place.
        September 18, 1866. Ezra Cornell to Theodore Townsand:
        "?I then found that the land scrip would only sell for about fifty cents per acre in the large quantity offered, and I further proposed to purchase the scrip of the state, select good lands and locate the scrip thereon and sell the land as opirtunity offered, giving to the "Cornell University" all the profits arising from the sale of land, thus realizing two or three dollars per acre as we hope to do instead of fifty cents per acre by the sale of the scrip.
        The Legislature accepted this proposition, and passed an act last session authurising the comptroller to sell the scrip to me on such conditions. In my agreement with the comptroller for the purchase of the scrip, I am to give him a mortgage on the land located as colateral security for the performance of my agrrement to pay the profits arising from the sale of the land over to the University, or to assign to the comptroller the Register certificate for the same purpose."
        Cornell, D.B.; Townsand, T.; Cornell, J.W.
      - October 6, 1866 - October 29, 1866 (Box 28, Folder 9)
        Telegraph business correspondence: stock; cattle; agriculture; Photo-lithography business; Cornell University: recommendations for faculty; Chicago Historical Society.
        Johnson, B.P.; Cornell, D.B.; Pollock, G.H.; Cornell, J.W.; Curtiss, George; Hillhouse, Thomas; White, Andrew Dickson.
      - October 30, 1866 - November 13, 1866 (Box 28, Folder 10)
        Cornell University: trustees, offers of collections; land scrip; Minnesota lands; Wisconsin lands; Chicago Historical Society; Kansas lands.
        October 31, November 4, 1866. Horace Greeley to Ezra Cornell concerning his resignation from the Board of Trustees of Cornell University.
        November 6, 1866. W.A. Woodward to Ezra Cornell from New York concerning a proposal to connect a Medical College about to be established in New York City with Cornell University.
        White, Andrew Dickson; Sibley, Hiram; Parker, J.M.; Andrews, G.H.; Bell, J.E.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Kelly, William; Woodward, W.A.; Morgan, E.; Cornell, D.B.; Geddes, George.
      - November 18, 1866 - November 27, 1866 (Box 28, Folder 11)
        Cornell University: faculty, donations; committee to consider Medical College; Wisconsin lands; telegraph business correspondence.
        November 24, 1866. William Kelly to Ezra Cornell:
        "I write to congratulate you upon the election of our friend Senator White to the Presidency of the Cornell University, and to express my sincere gratification that we are to have the benefit of his intelligence, experience and energy in that responsible position."
        Woodward, W.A.; Wood, Phebe; Kelly, William; White, Andrew Dickson; Cornell, Betsy Ann.
      - November 28, 1866 - December 17, 1866 (Box 28, Folder 12)
        Cornell University: extension of opening, committee to consider Medical College; agriculture; Wisconsin lands; land scrip; railroads.
        November 30, 1866. Andrew Dickson White to Ezra Cornell:
        "I have thought much since arriving home upon the possible extension of time by the recent Act of Congress. We ought not to procrastinate to anything like the extent allowed by the law but we might put off the reception of students and the beginning to pay professors salaries for a year and be, I am inclined to think, in much better position for it?"
        Geddes, George; White, Andrew Dickson; Chace, Thomas; Cornell, J.M.; Cornell, D.B.; Gurnsey, E.; Pinkham, Anna H.; Woodward, W.A.; Putnam, H.C.; Kyes, Eliza; Murdock, L.; Rooker, Thomas N.; Carey, F.G.
      - December 18, 1866 - December 27, 1866 (Box 28, Folder 13)
        Wisconsin State Historical Society; Cornell Public Library; Cornell University: faculty; Photo-lithography business.
        December 24, 1866. John Stanton Gould to Ezra Cornell discussing Cornell University's postponement of opening, and possible faculty members.
        Speed, J.J.; Gould, John Stanton; Chace, Thomas; Rice, V.M.; Page, John R.; Hopkins, P.A.
      - December 28, 1866 - December 31, 1866 (Box 28, Folder 14)
        Agriculture; New York State Legislature.
        Bell, J.E.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Pew, W.P.; Hopkins, P.A.; Chace, Miller; Chester, E.W.
    - Correspondence :: Ezra Cornell Correspondence :: 1867-1868
      - January 1, 1867 - January 12, 1867 (Box 28, Folder 15)
        Photo-lithography business; temperance; Cornell University: faculty; Cornell Public Library.
        Rooker, Thomas N.; Pinkham, F.W.; Hopkins, P.A.
      - January 13, 1867 - January 21, 1867 (Box 28, Folder 16)
        Telegraph business correspondence; railroads; New York State Legislature: letters from constituents; Cornell University; New York State Lunatic Asylum; Ithaca school building; telescopes; Wisconsin State Historical Society.
        Ithaca; Wisconsin.
        Curtiss, George; Chace, Thomas; Chester, E.W.; Rooker, Thomas N.; Cornell, E.B.; Drake, Mary J.; Cornell, D.B.; Boyle, C.B.
      - January 22, 1867 - January 27, 1867 (Box 28, Folder 17)
        Telegraph business correspondence; agricultural machinery; Cornell family genealogy and history; Photo-lithography business; railroads; cattle.
        January 24, 1867. F.M. Finch to Ezra Cornell concerning Cornell University and Cornell Public Library.
        Cook, A.E.; Rooker, Thomas N.; Finch, F.M.
      - January 28, 1867 - February 4, 1867 (Box 29, Folder 1)
        Western Union Telegraph Company; Wisconsin lands; Grinnell College; Vassar College.
        Horner, John; Cornell, E.B.; Chace, Thomas; Gould, John Stanton; Sibley, Hiram.
      - February 5, 1867 - February 13, 1867 (Box 29, Folder 2)
        New York State Legislature: letters from constituents and others, legislation; Cornell University: buildings, plan.
        February 9, 1866. D.B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell:
        "Military fame & Glory is a fine thing for a well clad back & a full belly, but it is of less account to a hungry man than a lb of pork or a peck of beans."
        Robertson, Mary C.; Finch, F.M.; Cornell, D.B.
      - February 14, 1867 - February 21, 1867 (Box 29, Folder 3)
        Cornell University: buildings, plan; women's education; Cornell family genealogy and history; cattle; mineralogical collection; New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents and others; homeopathy.
        February 17, 1867. Ezra Cornell to Eunice Cornell:
        "My Dear Grand Daughter. Your little letter came duly to hand and I was very glad to hear from you, and grand Ma was also very glad to hear from. I shall be very glad when I get through with the business here so I can go home and see you and your little brothers, and have you and them go with me up on the hill to see how the workmen get along with the building of the Cornell University where I hope you and your brothers and your cousins and a great many more children will go to school when they get large enough and will learn a great many things that will be useful to them and make them wise and good women and men. I want to have girls educated in the University as well as boys, so that they may have the same opportunity to become wise and useful to society that the boys have. I want you to keep this letter until you grow up to be a woman and want to go to a good school where you can have a good opertunity to learn, so you can show it the President and Faculty of the University to let them know that it is the wish of your Grand Pa, that girls as well as boys should be educated at the Cornell University."
        Schuyler, G.W.; Cornell, Eunice; Robertson, Mary C.; Chace, Eliza A.; Morgan, E.D.
      - February 22, 1867 - February 28, 1867 (Box 29, Folder 4)
        Western Union Telegraph Company; New York State Legislature: letters from constituents and others, legislation; mineralogical collection; sugar beet industry.
        February 1867. Draft of an address from Ezra Cornell to the Trustees concerning the planning for and building of the University and financial conditions.
        Wood, Phebe; Hopkins, P.A.
      - March 1, 1867 - March 8, 1867 (Box 29, Folder 5)
        Wisconsin lands; telegraph industry: stocks; telescope; New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents and others.
        Casey, Eliza; Cook, Ann E.; McGraw, Joseph; Wood, Phebe; Robertson, Mary C.
      - March 9, 1867 - March 13, 1867 (Box 29, Folder 6)
        New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents and others; sugar beet industry; Wisconsin lands; Cornell University: buildings; Cornell villa; New York State Inebriate Asylum; Smithsonian Institute; Cascadilla Institute; Susquehanna Bridge; Binghamton Charter; Cornell Public Library.
        Binghamton, N.Y.
        Cornell, D.B.; Sibley, Hiram; Cornell, E.B.; Nivison, S.S.; Finch, F.M.; Baird, Spencer T.
      - March 14, 1867 - March 18, 1867 (Box 29, Folder 7)
        Cornell University: buildings, establishment of Library, Natural History Collection; New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents and others; Smithsonian Institute; telegraph industry; Western Union Telegraph Company; cattle; Binghamton Charter; New York State railroads.
        March 16, 1867. Hiram Sibley to Ezra Cornell:
        "I went to Washington had an interview with Mr. Seward and the Russian Minister. They both agree that the Company done right in Suspending the work But Still think the line will be needed for Political reasons."
        March 16, 1867. H.W. Sage to Ezra Cornell:
        "Can you attend Church at Beeches tomorrow morning -- sit with me?I want to talk with you about several matters & shall feel obliged for such an interview -- If your wife's with you bring her"
        Binghamton; New York City.
        Finch, F.M.; Sibley, Hiram; Sage, H.W.; Baird, Spencer T.
      - March 19, 1867 - March 23, 1867 (Box 29, Folder 8)
        New York State Legislature: letters from constituents and others, legislation; elevated railway (New York City); Cornell University: buildings, establishment of Library, trustees; Cornell villa; New York State railroads; Binghamton Charter.
        New York City; Brooklyn; Binghamton; Batavia, N.Y.
        Cornell, E.B.; Kelly, William; Grant, E.B.
      - March 24, 1867 - March 27, 1867 (Box 29, Folder 9)
        Wisconsin lands; Cornell University: buildings, establishment of Library; Forest Park farm; grapes; elevated railroads; Susquehanna Bridge; Binghamton Charter.
        March 27, 1867. T.N. Rooker to Ezra Cornell:
        "Dont forget about the missing documents in regard to the Library Dedication."
        New York City; Binghamton.
        Cornell, John H.; Rooker, Thomas N.
      - March 28, 1867 - March 31, 1867 (Box 29, Folder 10)
        Binghamton Charter; New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents and others; Eight Hour Bill; Wisconsin lands; Cornell University: collections; Western Union Telegraph Company; telegraph industry.
        Binghamton; Brooklyn.
        Root, E.O.; Doubleday, A.; Rooker, Thomas N.; Tenney, Sanborn.
      - April 1, 1867 - April 6, 1867 (Box 29, Folder 11)
        Cornell University: buildings, plan; New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents and others; child labor laws; Wisconsin lands; cattle; Binghamton Charter.
        Chester, E.W.; Brown, Amos.
      - April 8, 1867 - April 12, 1867 (Box 29, Folder 12)
        People's College; New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents and others; agriculture; Cornell University: buildings, finances.
        Brooklyn.
        Brown, Amos; Rooker, Thomas N.; Darling, Charles A.; Cornell, D.B.; Faxton, Theodore S.; Finch, F.M.
      - April 13, 1867 - April 24, 1867 (Box 29, Folder 13)
        New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents and others; New York State canals; Wisconsin lands; Cornell University: buildings; Cornell family genealogy and history.
        Rooker, Thomas N.; Glenny, William; Wilcox, H.U.; Sibley, Hiram; Cook, Ann E.
      - April 25, 1867 - May 7, 1867 (Box 29, Folder 14)
        Cornell University: buildings; Williams College; New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents and others.
        April 26, 1867. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell:
        "White went to Buffalo last night, undecided yet which building to put up next."
        Binghamton; Ithaca.
        Tenney, Sanborn; Curtiss, George; White, Andrew Dickson; Wood, O.S.; Jewett, E.
      - May 8, 1867 - May 24, 1867 (Box 29, Folder 15)
        Telegraph industry: European lines; Cornell University: landscaping; cattle.
        May 12, 1867. Mary Ann Cornell to Ezra Cornell:
        "Mary writes she wants some money very much. I don't know why she always applies to me for money for I have none for her, nor any way to get any that I know of."
        Wood, O.S.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Cornell, D.B.; Garfield, Charles L.; White, Andrew Dickson; Rice, E.T.
      - May 25, 1867 - June 11, 1867 (Box 29, Folder 16)
        Cornell University: buildings, finances, establishment of Library; military education; agriculture; railroads; Western Union Telegraph Company; Smithsonian Institution.
        May 26, 1867. Mary Ann Cornell to Ezra Cornell: